const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",a="englishlit",o=200,i=120,t=[{id:336,question:"The end of “Give Me The Minstrel’s Seat”, seems to suggest that one needs the",option:{a:"support of others",b:"complete command of one’s wives",c:"support of one’s kinsmen",d:"aid of poets"},section:"based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New poetry from Africa; Soyinka W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa: Senanu, K E and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eels.): Exam Focus: Lit-erature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination guides; Nwoga, D.I (ed.): West African Verse andAdeoti G: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:512,question:"A literary work in which the characters an events are used as symbols is known as",option:{a:"Characteristics",b:"Allegory",c:"Metaphor",d:"Parallelism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:31,question:"Face thrives on ",option:{a:"big events ",b:"promotion ",c:"absurdity ",d:"incidents."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:382,question:"Yaremi in a dilemma, not knowing whether she is to shed tears of ",option:{a:"Gratitude or tears of sorrow",b:"Ingratitude or tears of Joy",c:"Gratitude or tears of joy",d:"Happiness"},section:"Question 21 is based on Bayo Adebowale's Lonely Days",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:479,question:"Dramatis personae in a play refers to",option:{a:"List of characters",b:"Order of appearance",c:"Cast list",d:"Protagonist and antagonist"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:15,question:"Which of these best defined exposition in drama? ",option:{a:"the author’s own general introduction to the play  ",b:"the author’s early exposure of his dramatis personae to conflict ",c:"introduction to the characters and the general problem with which the play deals ",d:"the first performance of the play on stage "},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:467,question:"Alfred Tennyson's Crossing the Bar. The use of imagery in the poem occurs in two broad, which are",option:{a:"Broad and straight",b:"Visual and audio",c:"Feelings and happiness",d:"Symbolism and imagery"},section:"Questions 26 to 30 are based on the John Hayward. The Golden Treasury of longer poema, selected and edited by Ernest. English Romantic Verse edited by Wright, Penguin books. A Pageant of longer poems edited by E,W Parker, Longman",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:309,question:"The expression “The child is the father of the man” in the poem above is an example of",option:{a:"paradox",b:"metaphor",c:"simile",d:"ellipsis"},section:"based on Literary Appreciation.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:313,question:"James Ofosu’s desire is to see Maanan trained as",option:{a:"a choreographer",b:"an attorney",c:"an accountant",d:"a surgeon"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:8,question:'Caliph: "Atthiru invites Mallam because ',option:{a:"Mallam has offended the caliph ",b:"Mai Worno needs to be talked to ",c:"Attahiru wants Mallam to explain the dream he had ",d:"Mallam and Mai Wurno are friends "},section:"question is on Attahiru, Ahmed Yerima's play",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:312,question:"In the play, the character of Lawyer B is represented through the use of",option:{a:"flashback",b:"dialogue",c:"play-within-the-play",d:"irony"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:304,question:"The image depicted is one of",option:{a:"destruction",b:"dejection",c:"happiness",d:"admiration."},section:"based on Literary Appreciation.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:420,question:"On a Friday night a few weeks later, packing boxes filled the younger apartment in prepartion for the move to their new house in a",option:{a:"White neighbourhood",b:"Black neighbourhood",c:"Outskirt of the neighbourhood",d:"City"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:314,question:"The plot of the play is,",option:{a:"linear",b:"cyclical",c:"complicated",d:"episodic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:508,question:"The speech was directed to",option:{a:"Cassio",b:"Lago",c:"Roderigo",d:"Othello"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:386,question:"Bigger arrives at the Dalton's house and wastes no time in his efforts to ascertain the situation with",option:{a:"Mary's disapperance",b:"Mary's corpse",c:"Mary's situation",d:"Mary's Happiness"},section:"Question 25 is based on Amma Darko's Faceless",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:137,question:"From this passage, the people that the writer admire are  ",option:{a:"poor  ",b:"brilliant   ",c:"rich   ",d:"unassuming "},section:`(Extract for question)
The human beings who I most admire are those without sterling qualities but are extraordinary in their ordinariness, the unsung heroes who will never be in the limelight or boulevard of fame, people who do great things when no one is watching or those who are not marked with the maple leaves of chieftaincy titles. They only wear fate, hard work, perseverance, anonymity and time. Yet, they are passionate, caring, visionary, sincere, determined and honest. These qualities mold those that are special without being aware. I strive to stay true to some of these qualities that I admire. To find a person with a few of these qualities is rare these days. To know someone who has all of them is amazing and a true blessing. [Excerpt from Tomorrow Left Us Yesterday-Tayo Olafioye]
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:226,question:"The traditional order in the play is represented by",option:{a:"Mrs. B",b:"Hannah",c:"Maanan",d:"Aunt"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:288,question:"Marvel’s To ‘His Coy Mistress’ is written mainly in",option:{a:"alternate rhymes",b:"blank verse",c:"heroic couplets",d:"middle rhymes."},section:"Based on selected poems from Johnson, 	R. et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyirvka, W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; Maduka, C.T. et al: Exam Focus: Literature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D. I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G.: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:81,question:"As literacy form the short  story is most closely related to ",option:{a:"the discourse ",b:"the novel  ",c:"story telling  ",d:"poetry "},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:227,question:"Where does the play take place?",option:{a:"On the street",b:"In George’s place",c:"In Aunt’s house",d:"In Ofosu’s place"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:3,question:"Which of these best describes setting in a novel? ",option:{a:"the place where an event takes place ",b:"the time when an event takes place ",c:"the place and time of an event ",d:"the back ground of an event "},section:"question is on William Shakespeare's hamlet",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:225,question:"Maanan expresses dislike for Lawyer B because of",option:{a:"his condemnation of  her choice career",b:"his recent advances towards her",c:"the betrayal of her father’s trust",d:"the betrayal of his wife’s trust"},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s  	Sons and Daughter. ",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:180,question:"The rhyme scheme of the stanza is",option:{a:"abcabcc",b:"ababcdd",c:"babaccc",d:"bcbccaa"},section:"Pan, O great Pan, to thee'<br> 		Thus do we sing!<br> 		Thou who keep’st chaste and free<br> 		As the young spring<br> 		Ever be thy honour spake<br> 		From that place the morn is broke<br> 		To the place day doth unyoke",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:388,question:"With a little coercion, a touch of blackmail, and a bit of deceit, poison is made to meet",option:{a:"Kabira and Sylv Po",b:"Mute and Kabria",c:"Fofo and Baby T",d:"Onko and Baby T"},section:"Question 27 is based on Amma Darko's Faceless",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:424,question:"The pepper strong enough to push scorpions. This expression illustrates the use of",option:{a:"Euphemism",b:"Personification",c:"Irony",d:"Satire"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:503,question:"Who responded to the speech?",option:{a:"Lago",b:"Cassio",c:"Othello",d:"Lodovico"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:455,question:"____________ investigates Baby T's death",option:{a:"Fofo",b:"Ma Tsuru",c:"Mute",d:"Kabria"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:416,question:"Kindo returns to find Mangu and queries him for giving ",option:{a:"Gin drink and evil smelling tobacco",b:"A negative advice",c:"A profitable advice",d:"Warning concerning the white man"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:422,question:"What eyes will watch our large mouths? What ear to our pitiful anger, what heart will listen to our clamoring? Illustrate",option:{a:"Irony",b:"Metonymy",c:"Synecdoche",d:"Fable"},section:"Question 21 to 25 are based on poems of Black Africa, edited by Wole Soyinka. A selection of African Poetry by K.E Senanu and T. Vincent. New poetry from Africa. Johnson etal. Poems from Ghana edited by Kofi Awoonor. Manscape in the Sierra, New and collected poems by Gbanabom Hallowell",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:67,question:"The literary technique in which a reader is taken to the past of a current action in known as:",option:{a:"rewinding ",b:"fast forward ",c:"flashback ",d:"repetition."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:284,question:"‘The experts, of course Disagree. The urine test they ordered Said, Negative.’ The lines above from Acqah’s “In the Navel of the Soul” depict",option:{a:"contradiction",b:"inevitability",c:"progress",d:"awareness."},section:"Based on selected poems from Johnson, 	R. et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyirvka, W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; Maduka, C.T. et al: Exam Focus: Literature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D. I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G.: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:376,question:"A short, carefully phrased expressed meant to elicit amusement and surprise is",option:{a:"Wit",b:"Tercet",c:"Hyperbole",d:"Limerick"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:536,question:"Invisible man refers directly to the identity of which character?",option:{a:"The narrator",b:"Dr. Bledsoe",c:"The narrator",d:"Norton"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:327,question:"The only two sons of Meka die fighting for",option:{a:"independence",b:"the colonialists",c:"the church",d:"the in people."},section:"based on Ferdinand Oyono’s,  	The Old Man and the Medal.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:540,question:'Whose words "keep the Nigger boy running"?',option:{a:"Tatlock",b:"His father",c:"His grandfather",d:"Mr. Norton"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:238,question:"The Ministry of Peace is concerned with making",option:{a:"instruments",b:"weapons",c:"wars",d:"reconciliation"},section:"Based on George Orwell’s  	Nineteen Eighty-Four.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:319,question:`‘...So tedious is this day<br>
	As is the night before some festival<br>
	To an impatient child that hath new robes<br>
	And may not wear them.’<br>
The literary device used in the excerpt is`,option:{a:"euphemism",b:"simile",c:"sarcasm",d:"bathos"},section:"based on William Shake¬speare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:98,question:"“The experts, of course disagree the urine test they ordered ‘said, Negative’. The lives above from acqah’s in the Nanel of the soul depict ",option:{a:"awareness ",b:"inevitability ",c:"progress ",d:"contradiction."},section:"Question is based on selected poems",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:315,question:"What causes the strained relationship between James and Lawyer B?",option:{a:"Betrayal of trust",b:"Standard of education",c:"Working experience",d:"Family differences"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:292,question:"An interlude is a brief",option:{a:"presentation in the interval of a dramatic performance",b:"play before the main dramatic performance",c:"presentation after the main dramatic performance",d:"dialogue between two persons."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:477,question:"A funny incident within a serious situation is",option:{a:"Comedy",b:"Comic relief",c:"Tragicomedy",d:"Tragic hero"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:147,question:"The national day in The Old Man and the Medal is  ",option:{a:"1st of October  ",b:"27th of May  ",c:"12th June  ",d:"14th July"},section:`Question is based on Ferdinand Oyono’s
The Old Man and medal and The joys of motherhood   
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:163,question:"The protagonist of the novel is  ",option:{a:"Nwokocha Agbadi ",b:"Nnaife  ",c:"Nwakusor ",d:"Nnu Ego."},section:"Question is based on Buchi Emecheta’s The Joys of Motherhood.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:248,question:"Pun as a literary device deals with",option:{a:"placing two opposite phrase",b:"placing words side by side",c:"playing on words",d:"arrangement of words"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:293,question:"An epic is a heroic story which includes",option:{a:"ballad",b:"lyric",c:"myth",d:"dialogue."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:258,question:"The speaker in the excerpt above is",option:{a:"hopeless",b:"uncertain",c:"afraid",d:"confident"},section:"Don’t panic. Be calm. If you are somehow upset.... try to regain your exposure.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:152,question:"Joe de Graft’s Sons and daughters is an example of ",option:{a:"domestic comedy ",b:"dark comedy ",c:"restoration comedy ",d:"comedy of error"},section:"Question is  based  on Joe de Graft’s Sons and Daughters.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:533,question:"One of the universal themes of the novel is",option:{a:"Vengeance",b:"Property and inheritance",c:"Religious hypocrisy",d:"Marriage"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:271,question:"The chorus in the prologue of the play is essentially meant to",option:{a:"foreshadow the play",b:"highlight the characters",c:"estimate the actions",d:"introduce the play."},section:"Based on George Orwell’s Nineteen  	Eighty-Four.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:35,question:"Periphrasis in poetic diction is marked by ",option:{a:"circumlocution ",b:"irony ",c:"proverb ",d:"parable."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2007"},{id:6,question:"The period Tess spends at Talbothays is the period of her:",option:{a:"the happiest period of her life ",b:"the period she suffers most horribly in the novel ",c:"the period she falls into temptation ",d:"the period when she became pregnant "},section:"question is on Thomas hardy's Tess of the d'Urbervilles",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:513,question:"Characterization in a novel refers to the",option:{a:"Writer's opinion of the characters",b:"Way the characters are revealed to the reader",c:"Characters and the way they behave",d:"Reader's opinion of the characters"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:135,question:"The extract is an example of  ",option:{a:"pun  ",b:"hyperbole  ",c:"Irony  ",d:"parody"},section:`(Extract for question )
Blessed Nigerians,
Who eat pestilence to sleep
Blessed the poor 
Who inherit thorns. . . . . . 
`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:507,question:"The above speech was made by",option:{a:"Othello",b:"Lago",c:"Desdemona",d:"Roderigo"},section:`Question 26 to 30 are based on William Shakespeare's "Othello". I have no great devotion to the deed. And yet he hath given me satisfying reasons. Tis but a man gone forth, ny sword; he dies.`,image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:470,question:'In "the pulley" the reason why God took the decision to withhold rest, the most important of all his gifts, from man is revealed in',option:{a:"Second stanza",b:"First stanza",c:"Third stanza",d:"Fourth stanza"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:291,question:"In Cope’s <em>Sonnet VII</em>, poetry is",option:{a:"a popular act",b:"a boring act",c:"an idle hobby",d:"a useless undertaking."},section:"Based on selected poems from Johnson, 	R. et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyirvka, W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; Maduka, C.T. et al: Exam Focus: Literature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D. I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G.: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:247,question:"A plot structure that defies chronology can be described as",option:{a:"open-ended",b:"circular",c:"episodic",d:"organic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:333,question:"‘Pregnant clouds Ride Safely on its back’ Pregnant clouds in Rubadiri’s “An AfricanThunderstorm implies”",option:{a:"uncertainty",b:"calmness",c:"disbelief",d:"fertility"},section:"based on selected poems from Ker, D. et al (eds.) New poetry from Africa; Soyinka W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa: Senanu, K E and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African poetry; Umukoro, M et al (eels.): Exam Focus: Lit-erature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination guides; Nwoga, D.I (ed.): West African Verse andAdeoti G: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:487,question:'In William Morris "The Proud King". The rhyme scheme for the seven line stanzas is consistent it is',option:{a:"aabbcc",b:"ababbcc",c:"abcdee",d:"abccddeeff"},section:"Question 6 to 10 are based on poems from the penguin book of English verse by John Hayward. The Golden Treasury of longer poems, selected and edited by Ernest. English Romantic Verse edited by Wright Penguin book. A Pageant of longer poems edited by E.W. Parker, Longman.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:186,question:"The use of imagery in prose or verse",option:{a:"appeals to the senses",b:"develop the plot",c:"create confusion",d:"obscures meaning"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:187,question:"The lines illustrate",option:{a:"soliloquy",b:"parallelism",c:"dialogue",d:"contrast"},section:"Our leaders will not compromise freedom<br> 	Nor will our heads give up liberty.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:378,question:"The setting of the blood of a stranger is a village called",option:{a:"Biang",b:"Mando",c:"Mampama",d:"Konkp"},section:`Question 16 to 20 are based on Dele Charley's "The Blood of a Stranger"`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:228,question:"‘O’ deadly sin! O rude unthankfulness! Thy fault our law calls death, but the kind Prince, Taking thy 		part, hath rushed aside the law and turned that black word.....’ Deadly sin refers to the",option:{a:"suicide of Juliet",b:"suicide of  Romeo",c:"murder of  Paris",d:"murder of  Tybalt"},section:"Based on William Shakespeare’s  	Romeo and Juliet.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:102,question:"De graft’s Sons and Daughters is structured into: ",option:{a:"three acts ",b:"four scenes ",c:"two acts ",d:"five Episodes."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:352,question:`Biokun:  I did it for her! Let them laugh!<br>
				Let them condemn me. I who have always <br>	
				derided superstition. I have gone bach to the <br>
				shrine of Olokun. At least if he dies, Oroki <br>
				will know I tried everything. <br>
				(Femi I Qsofisan: No More the Wasted Breed)<br>
Biokun’s mood in this passage is one of`,option:{a:"desperation",b:"frustration",c:"anger",d:"anxiety"},section:"based on Literary Appreciation",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:11,question:"Which of the following statement is most true about poetry?  ",option:{a:"the meanings of words are more important than their sounds  ",b:"the sounds of words are more important than their meanings  ",c:"the sounds of words are often more important than their meaning  ",d:"sounds and meanings of words are of little consequence "},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:126,question:"The exclusive right given to authors to protect their works from unlawful production or reproduction is   ",option:{a:"A copyright  ",b:"an authority to write  ",c:"an author’s right   ",d:"a constitutional provision "},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2012"},{id:544,question:'"Lord, what fools these mortals be!" In the line above, the character is',option:{a:"Expressing the behaviour of the lovers",b:"Expressing the love between two lovers",c:"Expressing the exaggerated silliness of the lovers behaviour",d:"Expressing the gift of God in their lives"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:502,question:"Who made the above speech?",option:{a:"Othello",b:"Lago",c:"Bianca",d:"Cassio"},section:`Questions 21 to 25 are based on William Shakespeare's "Othello". Let the devil and his dam haunt you! What did you mean by that same handkerchief, yon gave me even now?`,image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:283,question:"Rubadiri’s <em>An African Thunderstorm</em> appeals to the readers’ sense of",option:{a:"sight and taste",b:"feeling and sight",c:"smell, taste and hearing",d:"sight, smell and hearing."},section:"Based on selected poems from Johnson, 	R. et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyirvka, W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; Maduka, C.T. et al: Exam Focus: Literature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D. I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G.: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:214,question:"Ariel has ‘come’ because",option:{a:"he has been invited by Prospero",b:"he wants to make a request",c:"he desires a meeting",d:"flying is no problem to him"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br>  		Ariel:	All hail, great master! Grave sir, hail! I come<br> 			To answer thy best pleasure; be’t to fly, <br> 			To swim, to dive into the fire, to ride<br> 			On the curled clouds, to thy strong bidding task<br> 			Ariel and all his quality. <br> 			(Act I, Scene  Two, lines 189 - 193)	",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:249,question:"In a narrative poem, the poet attempts to",option:{a:"summarize a story",b:"describe a place",c:"preach a sermon",d:"tell a story"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:364,question:"Marlow and Hastings are in an argument over when to see",option:{a:"Kate",b:"Constance",c:"Tony",d:"Mrs. Hardcastle"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:296,question:"Oxymoron is the use of two contrasting words that are",option:{a:"placed far apart",b:"different in meaning",c:"placed side by side",d:"similar in meaning."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:374,question:"A port's use of regular rhythm is know as ",option:{a:"Metre",b:"Assonance",c:"Allegory",d:"Onomatopoeia"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:79,question:"Assonance poetry is the repetition of ",option:{a:"internal vowels in words ",b:"consonant sounds in words ",c:"final sounds at the end of a line 1 ",d:"final sounds at the beginning of a line"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:557,question:"The flat character in a literary work",option:{a:"Is the same as the round character",b:"Cannot be found in an allegory",c:"Is capable of growing",d:"Always embodies a quality"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:256,question:"The subject matter of the extract above is",option:{a:"Storm",b:"sea waves",c:"house movement",d:"earthquake"},section:"But the towering earth was tired sitting in one position. She moved, suddenly, and the houses crumbled, the mountains heaved horribly, and the work of a million years was lost	",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:413,question:"Aloho has discovered that she is pregnant for chief, downcast, she sobs _____________ console's her",option:{a:"Ochuole",b:"Ogeyi",c:"ACP Yakubu",d:"Madam Hoha"},section:`Question 12 and 13 are based on Fran Ogeche's "Harvest of Corruption"`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:110,question:"In Gbemisola Adeoti’s Naked Soles”, the expression red milk of grief’ refers to: ",option:{a:"wine  ",b:"Ink ",c:"blood ",d:"palm-oil"},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:543,question:"The image in the quotation above depicts the speaker's",option:{a:"Hatred",b:"Desperation",c:"Love",d:"Disregard"},section:`Questions 22 to 26 are based on William Shakespeare's A Midsummer Night's Dream. "Ay me, for ought that I could ever read, Could ever hear by tale or history, The course of true love. Never did run smooth…"`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:177,question:"The performers in a play constitute the",option:{a:"chorus",b:"characters",c:"audience",d:"cast"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:517,question:"A poet's use of regular rhythm is known as",option:{a:"Allegory",b:"Assonance",c:"Metre",d:"Onomatopoeia"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:310,question:"The technique employed in narrating the excerpt above is",option:{a:"flashback",b:"stream of consciousness",c:"foreshadowing",d:"play-within-the-play."},section:"based on Literary Appreciation.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:551,question:`The theme of beauty and strength in "Black Woman" by Leopold Sedar Senghor's is a`,option:{a:"Dramatic poem",b:"Narrative poem",c:"Short poem",d:"Negritude poem"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:301,question:"A literary work which imitates another in a distorted form is called",option:{a:"exodium",b:"isocohen",c:"metonymy",d:"burlesque."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:243,question:"Both comedy and tragedy have",option:{a:"happy ending",b:"climax",c:"tragic hero",d:"stanza"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:17,question:'Starving sod" here is: ',option:{a:"a metaphor ",b:"a personification ",c:"a simile ",d:"a paradox."},section:`question is on an extract form a poem by Thomas Hardy. Read the lines carefully and answer the question that follow:
We stood by a pond that winter day.
And the sun was white, as though children of God.`,image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2006"},{id:206,question:"The “impostor” is",option:{a:"Sebastian",b:"Antonio",c:"Ferdinand",d:"Alonso"},section:"	WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br> 		Silence! One word more<br> 		Shall make me chide thee, if not hate thee. What!<br> 		An advocate for an impostor! Hush!<br> 		(Act I, Scene Two, lines 478 - 480)",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:215,question:"Prospero has actually",option:{a:"raised a storm at sea",b:"punished Miranda",c:"dismissed Fedinand",d:"commanded Ariel to disappear"},section:"WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE: The Tempest<br><br>  		Ariel:	All hail, great master! Grave sir, hail! I come<br> 			To answer thy best pleasure; be’t to fly, <br> 			To swim, to dive into the fire, to ride<br> 			On the curled clouds, to thy strong bidding task<br> 			Ariel and all his quality. <br> 			(Act I, Scene  Two, lines 189 - 193)	",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:515,question:"In the theatre, words spoken by a character that are meant to be heard by the audience but not by the other characters on stage is called",option:{a:"Aside",b:"Soliloquy",c:"Acoustic",d:"Tone"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:545,question:"The traditional verse form of speech as dialogue in Midsummer Night's Dream is used to symbolize the",option:{a:"Impressiveness of the characters",b:"Intense feelings of the characters",c:"Traditionalist of the play",d:"Function of poetry in the play"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:522,question:"Midsummer Night's Dream is what type of play?",option:{a:"Tragedy",b:"Farce",c:"Comedy",d:"Tragic-comedy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:262,question:"In the play, Fasuwa represents the",option:{a:"new culture",b:"patriarchy",c:"old order",d:"African civilization."},section:"Based on J.C. De Graft’s Sons and  	Daughters.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:61,question:"A part from emphasis, what other effect does the repetition have?  ",option:{a:"makes the poem rhythmical  ",b:"makes the poem tedious  ",c:"makes the poem -notonous  ",d:"makes the poem exhilarating."},section:`Read the following extract from a poem to answer questions 
Among rocks, I am the loose one,
Among arrows, I am the heart
Among daughters, I am the recluse,
Among sons, the one who dies young
`,image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:111,question:"In Masizi Kunene’s “A Heritage of Liberation; this season’ refers to the period of: ",option:{a:"oppression ",b:"freedom  ",c:"migration  ",d:"resettlement"},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:475,question:"A plot in a literary work is about",option:{a:"Character delineation",b:"Casual arrangement of events",c:"Resolution of conflicts",d:"Law of poetic justice"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:463,question:"The panic of growing older. One of the themes is found in the above poem",option:{a:"Anxiety associated with ageing",b:"A forceful fusion",c:"Nostalgia",d:"Conflict of the way to go"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2018"},{id:510,question:"",option:{a:"Cyprus, A street",b:"Venice, A Street",c:"Venice, Another Street",d:"A seaport in Cyprus"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:115,question:"In China, according to D.H. Lawrence, bats are symbols of: ",option:{a:"death  ",b:"birth ",c:"caution ",d:"joy"},section:"Questions is based on Non-African Poetry",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:103,question:"The central  conflict in de Graft’s Sons and Daughter is primarily: ",option:{a:"political ",b:"generational ",c:"racial",d:"communal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:501,question:"Tony Steals the casket containing",option:{a:"Kate's Jewels",b:"Mrs. Hardcastles's Jewels",c:"Miss. Hardcastle's Jewel",d:"Constance's Jewels"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:353,question:`	‘My song is the root<br>
	touching other roots <br>
	in a covenant below the crust..’<br>
	(Niyi  Osundare: Waiting Laughters)<br>

The imagery used in the second line of the extract above is`,option:{a:"olfactory",b:"visual",c:"tactile",d:"auditory"},section:"based on Literary Appreciation",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"},{id:109,question:"Dancing through blooming thorns” in Gbemisola  Adeoti’s Naked soles” connotes: ",option:{a:"hoeing a field of thorns ",b:"dancing  in a keen competition ",c:"being merry amidst suffering",d:"playing flowers and plants."},section:"Question is are based on selected African poems.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2010"},{id:155,question:"In Andrew Marvell’s “To his Coy mistress”, the poet adopts a consistent rhyming scheme of ",option:{a:"sestet    ",b:"Couplet ",c:" tercet  ",d:"free verse"},section:"Question is based on African and Non-African Poetry  ",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2013"},{id:282,question:"The subject matter of Adeoti’s Naked Soles is",option:{a:"soul and mind",b:"hunger and strife",c:"suffering and despair",d:"hatred and bitterness."},section:"Based on selected poems from Johnson, 	R. et al (eds.): New Poetry from Africa; Soyirvka, W. (ed.): Poems of Black Africa; Senanu, K.E. and Vincent, T. (eds.): A Selection of African Poetry; Maduka, C.T. et al: Exam Focus: Literature in English; Eruvbetine, A. E. et al (eds.): Longman Examination Guides; Nwoga, D. I. (ed.): West African Verse and Adeoti G.: Naked Soles.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:300,question:"A figurative device in which a statement is made and then withdrawn is referred to as",option:{a:"metanoia",b:"metaphysical",c:"metalanguage",d:"metalepsis."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:200,question:"The theme of the poem is",option:{a:"the love of mother",b:"invoking the spirit of womanhood",c:"admiration for women’s hard work",d:"the suffering of women"},section:"Proud mothers of the coming age,<br> 		‘Tis good to find you now engage<br> 		Your minds and time your lives to raise<br> 		Above the level of bygone days<br> 		<br> 		‘Tis good to see you play your part<br> 		With spirit and undaunted heart,<br> 		It gives young Afric’s throbbing soul<br> 		A glimpse of a bright and glorious goal<br> 		<br> 		God bless you, mothers of our race,<br> 		God cause to shine on you His face;<br> 		And give you strength and all you crave<br> 		To bring forth sons and daughters brave.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:406,question:'The expression "Lay a sentence" means',option:{a:"Decide who is guilty",b:"Offer criticism",c:"Give advice",d:"Speak politely"},section:"Let me speak like yourself and Lay a sentence which, aas a grise or step may help these lovers when remedies are past, the griefs are ended, by seeing the worst which late on nopes depends. (Act I scene III)",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2017"},{id:370,question:"Farce thrives on",option:{a:"Big events",b:"Premonition",c:"Absurdity",d:"Incidents"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2016"},{id:302,question:"‘You do not have to be brutal to be a soldier, or rather you are brutal not because you are a soldier, but because there is a sadist, a rapist, a fascist and a murderer in you who is waiting for war and army uniforms to give them expression.’ ( Festus lyayi: Heroes ) The speaker here contends that",option:{a:"soldiers are generally wicked",b:"human nature has to do with a profession",c:"soldiers are characteristically gentle",d:"the latent brutality in man finds expression in war."},section:"based on Literary Appreciation.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:193,question:"__________ is a literary device used to express something unpleasant in a more acceptable manner",option:{a:"Epilogue",b:"Epigram",c:"Euphemism",d:"Eulogy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:496,question:"Bigger kills and throws Mary Dalton's remains in the ",option:{a:"Lagoon",b:"Street",c:"Furnace",d:"Pit"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:542,question:"The author's thematic concern is",option:{a:"Overcoming deception to reach the truth",b:"The ability to rise above defeat",c:"Relationship between the blacks and whites",d:"Actualising one's dreams"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:294,question:"Farce can be described as a dramatic piece marked by",option:{a:"movement from serious to the light-hearted mood",b:"comic and exaggerated actions",c:"actions devoid of meaning",d:"gloomy actions with momentary reliefs."},section:"Based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:69,question:"The speaker of the above except is a ",option:{a:"son of Lord Montague ",b:" nephew to Lady Capulet ",c:"kinsman to the Prince ",d:" servant to Paris."},section:'" ... This is a Montague, our foe; A villain, that is hither come in spit. To scorn at out solemnity this night. William Shakespeare: Romeo and Juliet I:V,61-63. ',image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"post-utme",examyear:"2008"},{id:528,question:`In D.H Lawrence's "BAT", the line "hang themselves up like an old rag" indicates the poet's _____________ of bats`,option:{a:"Love",b:"Hatred",c:"Kindness",d:"Acceptance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2020"},{id:498,question:"Chief Ade Haladu's crimes are made known to him in a",option:{a:"Police station",b:"Public place",c:"Court of law",d:"Hotel environment"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2019"},{id:342,question:"A poetic devices in which an idea in a line runs into another is called",option:{a:"rhyme scheme",b:"enjambment",c:"end rhyme",d:"pathos"},section:"based on General Literary Principles.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"utme",examyear:"2009"}],n={message:e,subject:a,status:200,total:120,data:t};export{t as data,n as default,e as message,o as status,a as subject,i as total};
